In this tutorial I will show you how to evaluate the step response
of an RC circuit using standard circuit techniques
Now by step response what we mean is that the voltage
or current applied to the circuit involves a jump
As you can see in this case our voltage source
initially is off before time "t" equal to 0
and jumps up to 12 volts at time t equal to zero.
We want to do in this case is evaluate the current through the
capacitor and at the same time
we'll also evaluate the voltage which is both the voltage on the capacitor and the voltage across the three kilo ohm resistor
now the key thing to remember about step response evaluation is that
we need to evaluate the time constant
initial and final values. Now each value
so the time constant we denote by tau and  tau
represents the value we'll see when we have this decaying exponential
e to the minus t over tau
response. In a circuit like the one
we're looking at, the voltages and currents
all experience the same time constant. The basic explanation for this is that
if you would imagine the
voltages on the six kilo ohm resistor and the three-kilo ohm resistor
they have to add up to a flat  value, so whatever
e to the minus t over tau  shape one as the other one also has to have the same shape
the same thing happened at the node when we are evaluating KCL